<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News and blog posts | N. R. Sommer</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>News and blog posts</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©Nathalie Sommer 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu5b137edab750718cfd6d38eb1d1fcf4f_43081_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>News and blog posts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to support nursing parents in graduate school</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I became a mom in the final few minutes of 2021 and entered the happiest, and hardest, phase of my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the decision to breastfeed with eyes wide open. I understood its benefits for me, for my baby, for our bond, for my bank account, and for the environment. I also knew there would be (potentially insurmountable) challenges, and I would need all the help I could get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got off to a rocky start. My newborn was nearly hospitalized after losing too much weight after birth. On the advice of her doctor, we tried — several times — offering formula. Each time ended in projectile vomit, and lots of tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mercifully, blessedly, thankfully, my university health plan covered unlimited visits with a lactation consultant. Within two weeks, we successfully established nursing. There were later bumps in the road (oversupply, then undersupply, then plugged ducts), but it no longer felt like a life-or-death situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my daughter was six weeks old, the first formula recall notice was issued. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/10/us/baby-formula-shortage.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;situation worsened throughout 2022&lt;/a&gt;. While the news coverage has slowed, on-the-ground shortage remains. Despite actively looking in every store I enter, I still have not seen formula on the shelves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My daughter is now 11 months old and has not needed formula supplementation, thanks in large part due to the support of my spouse, healthcare workers, and daycare providers. It is a deep privilege to exclusively breastfeed my daughter, a challenge and a bond that I am daily grateful for. Soon, I will no longer be my child&amp;rsquo;s primary source of nutrition, though we may continue nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I approach the end of my pumping journey, I felt compelled to write a long-form primer on breastfeeding, for people who have never been a nursing parent. Before giving you recommendations, here are the things you need to know about breastfeeding and pumping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-stuff-you-should-know&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;screen reader text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/nursing-support/should-know_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_181437_88b405b399bbbdd8ff13e81e16a146d8.webp 400w,
               /post/nursing-support/should-know_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_181437_2c2639d440b2cfe987a5713daf9b9cf2.webp 760w,
               /post/nursing-support/should-know_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_181437_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/should-know_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_181437_88b405b399bbbdd8ff13e81e16a146d8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;299&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Stuff You Should Know
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Lactation is maintained in a supply-demand relationship.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supply drops when there isn&amp;rsquo;t sufficient demand. This requires that milk is removed (by a baby or by a breast pump) with high frequency. A rule of thumb is &lt;em&gt;every three hours&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Milk needs to be removed from the breasts with high frequency.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If milk is not removed with high frequency, there is an immediate risk to the nursing parent ranging from engorgement and plugged ducts to mastitis. Missing even one feed or pump can be painful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Breast pumps are not a perfect substitute for direct breastfeeding.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pumping without proximity to your child can be stressful and psychologically taxing. Time apart from your child while exclusively pumping can still cause a drop in your supply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Human milk (or formula) is the primary source of nutrition for the first YEAR of life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://publications.aap.org/pediatrics/article-abstract/150/1/e2022057988/188347/Policy-Statement-Breastfeeding-and-the-Use-of/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American Academy of Pediatrics&lt;/a&gt; recommends exclusive nursing for the first six months of life. That means no formula supplementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solids can be introduced at six months, but human milk should remain the primary source of nutrition until twelve months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only after twelve months can cow&amp;rsquo;s milk be introduced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The AAP further recommends that nursing should continue through age 2 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Safe storage of human milk is logistically complex for working parents.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pumped milk needs to be kept in a refrigerator, and either be used within 4 days or frozen. Thawed milk needs to be used within 24 hours, and it can never be refrozen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In addition, some nursing parents may have excess lipase activity, causing a soap-like taste in thawed milk, which most infants refuse to take.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those still keeping track, milk pumped during the workday on Friday cannot be used on Monday without being frozen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-cdc-guidelines-for-human-milk-storage&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;screen reader text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/nursing-support/guidelines_hue28169edabfdf0d56e22890ff946481d_123840_80533da1728e1ab0f4835d1f4e2611df.webp 400w,
               /post/nursing-support/guidelines_hue28169edabfdf0d56e22890ff946481d_123840_654c2926c787d01c3e899c6a3b95978f.webp 760w,
               /post/nursing-support/guidelines_hue28169edabfdf0d56e22890ff946481d_123840_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/guidelines_hue28169edabfdf0d56e22890ff946481d_123840_80533da1728e1ab0f4835d1f4e2611df.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;474&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      CDC guidelines for human milk storage
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Parents who pump need clean, private spaces.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pumping needs to be done with clean hands, on clean surfaces, with clean pump parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some nursing parents may also require access to an outlet to operate or charge their pump.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if someone has a wearable pump, they will still need a clean space to remove the pump, transfer milk into a storage bag for refrigeration, and wash the pump parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;if-you-are-in-a-position-of-power-and-want-to-support-graduate-student-parents-keep-reading-while-this-is-generally-good-advice-for-supporting-student-parents-regardless-of-how-they-feed-their-children-i-offer-specific-recommendations-around-breastfeeding&#34;&gt;If you are in a position of power and want to support graduate student parents, keep reading. While this is generally good advice for supporting student-parents regardless of how they feed their children, I offer specific recommendations around breastfeeding.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-recommendations&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;screen reader text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/nursing-support/recommendations_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_151035_6ca717acacd31d27e38e667605bf020e.webp 400w,
               /post/nursing-support/recommendations_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_151035_b6f55ed23a85db4b99820cfc6082ba07.webp 760w,
               /post/nursing-support/recommendations_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_151035_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/recommendations_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_151035_6ca717acacd31d27e38e667605bf020e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;234&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Recommendations
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Talk to your students&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Before they return to in-person work, check in to offer your support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acknowledge that the transition can be challenging, physically and emotionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask if they will need the time and room space for nursing, and ensure the necessary systems are in place (see above). Legally, employees are entitled to some minimum standard of sufficient time and space to pump human milk. Ensure your basic compliance and support your sleep-deprived student.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Optimize the pumping space&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a private, clean space, in their primary building, with the ability to lock the room. Do not require a separate email message or approval to access the room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow for day-of room booking. Babies are unpredictable, and the night-before feeding schedule can often dictate the day-of pumping schedule. Similarly, research is also unpredictable. They may need to work at different times of day, or adjust if something goes wrong. Permit flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider providing some basics, like sterilizing wipes for surfaces, pump cleaning wipes, milk storage bags, and a mini fridge for daily storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Minimize or eliminate overnight travel and fieldwork&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;at least within the first six months, ideally for the first year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overnight travel is a prolonged period away from their infant, and a logistical nightmare for the safe storage of pumped milk. Some questions your student will have to answer: &lt;em&gt;Will there be a fridge? Can I reasonably carry pumped milk in a cooler bag? What about getting through airport security? If I am gone longer than 4 days, should I freeze it and express ship it home? How? Will my milk supply drop? How often do I need to pump to maintain my supply?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overnight travel also requires the nursing parent to plan significantly far in advance because their child still needs to eat while their food source is away. Building up a freezer stash of frozen milk can take a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fieldwork is dirty, with limited private space, and often conducted under a tremendous time crunch. Finding a clean environment to safely pump, with privacy and access to a charging port, for 20 minutes every three hours, then having to clean your pump parts, store the expressed milk in a cold place, and get it into a fridge before it expires&amp;hellip; Wearable pumps do not fix these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;give-your-student-the-ability-to-opt-in-but-do-not-require-them-to-travel-or-conduct-fieldwork&#34;&gt;Give your student the ability to opt-in, but do not require them to travel or conduct fieldwork.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Advocate for longer parental leave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all federal agencies and professional societies that handle some aspect of public health recommend that babies are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dietaryguidelines.gov/sites/default/files/2020-12/Dietary_Guidelines_for_Americans_2020-2025.pdf#page=65&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;exclusively breastfed for the first six months of life&lt;/a&gt;. This means that the lactating, usually birthing parent, is the infant&amp;rsquo;s sole and around-the-clock food source. For emphasis, babies eat &lt;em&gt;every 2 to 3.5 hours&lt;/em&gt;. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dol.gov/agencies/whd/fmla&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;protected parental leave in the United States&lt;/a&gt; is for only 12 weeks (unpaid), which is less than half the time of the exclusive breastfeeding period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an advocate for your graduate student, push for a minimum of six months of parental leave. As a direct supervisor, set up systems to allow your graduate student to stay home, at least within those first six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Advocate for affordable, on-site childcare.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On-site care makes everyone happier and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JMP-06-2012-0182/full/html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;makes parents more productive&lt;/a&gt;. Nursing is often faster than pumping because there is no necessary set up or cleaning. On-site childcare also means valuable hours aren&amp;rsquo;t being spent commuting to campus. And generally, proximity tends to decrease anxiety in parents, allowing them to focus on their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At universities, on-campus childcare is usually reserved as a perk for faculty, and sometimes for staff. The sky-rocketing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marketplace.org/2022/07/08/lack-of-affordable-child-care-keeping-women-out-of-workforce/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cost of childcare is keeping women out of the labor market&lt;/a&gt;, and the same is true for academia. As a reference point, the United States Department of Health and Human Services &lt;a href=&#34;https://bipartisanpolicy.org/blog/demystifying-child-care-affordability/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;says affordable childcare should not exceed 7% of a household&amp;rsquo;s annual income&lt;/a&gt;. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.care.com/about/press/majority-of-families-spend-at-least-20-of-household-income-on-childcare-according-to-new-care-com-survey/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;51% of parents say they spend more than 20% of household income on child care&lt;/a&gt; (I am in this group, with one child in part-time care).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an advocate for your graduate student, push for additional stipend towards childcare and reduced rates for on-campus care. As a direct supervisor, allow for flexible working arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen overnight, but little things can go a long way in supporting graduate student parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-if-academia-wants-to-retain-its-scholar-parentsparticularly-mothersit-needs-to-increase-support-for-family-life-these-recommendations-are-one-place-to-start&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;screen reader text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/nursing-support/end_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_313090_a90a82725532515a08ab2c5fb6c4ab7b.webp 400w,
               /post/nursing-support/end_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_313090_2a888e62a63d4e9a1bc13fd648688347.webp 760w,
               /post/nursing-support/end_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_313090_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/post/nursing-support/end_hu3a0063144fa60b702a61cc3db4cff908_313090_a90a82725532515a08ab2c5fb6c4ab7b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;316&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      If academia wants to retain its scholar-parents?particularly mothers?it needs to increase support for family life. These recommendations are one place to start.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview with WCAX Channel 3 News</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/wcax-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/wcax-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Vermont-based WCAX Channel 3 interviewed me about our NSF-funded project on climate variability, phenotypic plasticity, and ecosystem function. Watch it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wcax.com/2022/01/21/researchers-monitor-s-burlington-natural-area-climate-study/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for fellowship applications</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/tips-fellowship-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/tips-fellowship-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing a fellowship application (the NSF GRFP, Fulbright, Rhodes, Marshall, Soros, Schwartzman, etc.) is a daunting task. These applications take time, energy, and a lot of mental grit! Yet writing a fellowship application, regardless of the outcome, can provide clarity and direction. The opportunity to dive into your personal story as well as your interests and career goals, is a unique chance to critically examine your path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you will find some tips and guidance for helping you on your journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cast your net wide&lt;/strong&gt;: Oftentimes there is more than one fellowship opportunity that will help you reach your goal. For example, if you&amp;rsquo;d like to earn a Masters degree several different fellowships can help you attain that objective (Fulbright, Marshall, Rhodes, Mitchell, NSF GRFP). Casting your net wide and applying to several fellowships increases the likelihood you will be able to ultimately carry out your plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the instructions&lt;/strong&gt;: Does the grant have a strict word limit? Do they require certain citation formats or document settings? Do they require you to break your application into sections? Before you start, getting a handle on the specifics will help you structure your application to meet the requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get a feel for the grant&lt;/strong&gt;: Each fellowship has its own &amp;ldquo;personality&amp;rdquo;, so to speak. For example, the Fulbright commission cares deeply about international cultural exchange, while the Truman seeks a candidate that is a &amp;ldquo;change agent&amp;rdquo;. Often, simply looking at the fellowship&amp;rsquo;s website will give you a sense of what type of candidate the granting agency is excited about. Understanding the feel for the fellowship will help you decide if you are a good fit for the opportunity as well as provide context that you can use to tailor your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with a hook&lt;/strong&gt;: Opening a statement with a hook is an important step for engaging your reader. In a personal essay, start with a story that gives the reader a bit of insight into who you are as a person. In a research statement, think about the problem your research will address. How can you frame the work in an accessible way that gets the reader excited about the work you are going to do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use stories&lt;/strong&gt;: The best way for a committee to get to know you is to tell stories. Through stories, you are able to not only create an engaging narrative, but also provide insight into who you are as a person. In other words, show: don&amp;rsquo;t tell. Here is an example of both a statement, and a story that can better present the information in that statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statement: For my senior thesis, I won an Atlantic Coast Conference-International Academic Collaborative Research Grant to work in the lab of French Professor Jane Doe, conducting a paleoclimate reconstruction of Holocene temperatures in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story: I stumbled upon what became a life-changing opportunity during my semester abroad. Interested in a professor&amp;rsquo;s lecture on climate, I signed up for office hours. I expected to only get a few minutes to pick her brain, but to my surprise, I was the only student there. I was captivated by her research and personal story of being one of the first women in the field of paleoecology. Two hours later, I left inspired and fueled with passion to overcome my insecurities. I had a thesis topic and a commitment to science I no longer felt I needed to suppress. That spring I won an Atlantic Coast Conference-International Academic Collaborative Research Grant, which allowed me to return to France to conduct my own, independent paleoclimate reconstruction of the Holocene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the story, the author is able not only communicate the facts in the statement, but also give insight into the type of student they are. They are 1) the type of student who is willing to engage with professors, 2) a student who overcame insecurities, 3) able to work in international settings. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s much more interesting to read!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-essay-tips&#34;&gt;Personal Essay Tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t feel shackled to a chronological story&lt;/strong&gt;: When writing a personal statement it can be easy to tell your story chronologically: consider breaking out of this mold. After all, how many applications do you think the committee reads that start with a story or statement about the candidate&amp;rsquo;s childhood? Instead, think about how you can organize your essay around themes that demonstrate your skills. For example, organizing paragraphs that focus on your leadership, research, outreach, teaching, community involvement, etc. can help you write an essay that seamlessly time travels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be authentic&lt;/strong&gt;: Your essay should read like you wrote it, with all your personality traits and quirks! The best advice I have ever gotten was to have a close friend of family member read my first and last draft of my personal statements only for authenticity. Does what I wrote speak to me as a person? Often a trusted confidant can help you determine what is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show don&amp;rsquo;t tell&lt;/strong&gt;: This advice is so important it needs to be repeated! Using stories to demonstrate your skills, passions, and experiences will help you create an engaging essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-statement-tips&#34;&gt;Research Statement Tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider your audience: Each fellowship committee chooses their selection committee in a different way. Therefore, it is important to try to understand the audience for your fellowship. Is your reader going to be an expert in your field, or someone with more general knowledge? Understanding the reader will help you gauge how much detail and jargon to use. When in doubt, simplify!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a compelling argument, for you and your work: Your research statement is your chance to demonstrate your academic excellence as well as your curiosity and passion for your topic. You want to convince the reader that not only is your research cutting-edge and important, but also that you are uniquely qualified to do it. Consider trying to address the following in your essay: Why is your research important in this current moment? Why are you interested in your topic? How do both this fellowship and the research fit into your long-term plans? How are you prepared to carry out this research?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start early&lt;/strong&gt;: The most successful applications are the ones that have time to improve with drafts! You should expect to write anywhere between 4-7+ drafts, and therefore you should begin your application ~4 months out from the deadline. This will allow you to solicit several rounds of feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stick to only a few reviewers&lt;/strong&gt;: Asking advice from everyone might seem like a good idea, but often times it can be overwhelming. Choose 2-4 people from whom you will ask for feedback, and then show them multiple drafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solicit feedback once you have a draft&lt;/strong&gt;: Providing your reviewer with a draft, rather than an outline, will help the reviewer get a full picture of the application and be able to give concrete feedback. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean wait until you have a perfect draft: once you have a draft, share it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the application process may at time seem overwhelming this experience will help you discern your path moving forward. Additionally, it allows you to spend time and talk about you ideas with your recommendation letter writers. And, remember that no matter the outcome, just by submitting your application you&amp;rsquo;ve accomplished a difficult thing. With that, all that&amp;rsquo;s left is to wish you best of luck!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Come work with us!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/postbac-advert-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/postbac-advert-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://schmitz.environment.yale.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Schmitz Lab at the Yale School of the Environment&lt;/a&gt; is recruiting a recent grad for a 1-year paid fellowship. The fellow will design an independent project on any topic relating to food webs, ecosystem function, evolutionary ecology, and climate change, as part of a larger NSF project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fellow would be based in New Haven CT, with a flexible start date of Sept 1 2021. The fellow will work with the PIs, postdoc, and doctoral students to develop an independent research project, with the goal of generating a first-authored manuscript and presenting at conferences. We will also provide professional development to prepare the fellow for next steps in a STEM career or graduate school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fellow will be funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2021/nsf21085/nsf21085.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Science Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, specifically for recent grads who want to pursue a STEM career, but were unable to have a research experience as an undergraduate student due to pandemic-related interruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eligibility:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;US citizen or permanent resident&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed a bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree but not currently enrolled in another degree program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Priority placed on students from underrepresented groups, veterans, or those who have not participated in any kind of research experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some level of comfort around spiders and ticks (or willingness to be uncomfortable) is preferred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested folks should email &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:nathalie.sommer@yale.edu&#34;&gt;nathalie.sommer@yale.edu&lt;/a&gt; with a copy of their cv and brief biosketch (1-paragraph max). Applications for the NSF REPS program are due on July 2nd, so please get in touch as soon as possible. Consideration of candidates will begin June 25th.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview with the Yale Law, Ethics, and Animals Program (LEAP)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/leap-interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/leap-interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Yale Law, Ethics, and Animals Program (LEAP) interviewed me about my 2020 paper in &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ece3.6648&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution&lt;/a&gt; and upcoming conservation ethics projects. You can read the interview &lt;a href=&#34;https://law.yale.edu/yls-today/news/qa-nathalie-sommer-how-differences-grasshopper-personality-affect-ecosystems&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflecting on quals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/quals-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/quals-reflection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the moment, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t say quals was fun. I was in a moderate state of panic for the six weeks leading up to exams, and a last minute schedule change (that pushed my exams forward by five days) sent me into sheer terror. The written period was a complete blur. I burrowed into my couch and only left when my spouse coaxed me into neighborhood walks. In contrast, the oral exam is burned into my memory. One too many stumbles during my prospectus presentation, one too many long pauses while I tried to parse out the question from my committee. The infinity waiting in the Zoom breakout room to hear if I&amp;rsquo;d passed&amp;hellip; Then the floodgates opening with relief and surprise and pride when I passed with distinction and suddenly, it was all over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t experience a &lt;a href=&#34;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive_print.php?comicid=147&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post-quals slump&lt;/a&gt; so much as a post-quals dump. By that, I mean everything that I had put on pause came rushing back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dont-know-what-youve-got-til-its-gone&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t know what you&amp;rsquo;ve got til it&amp;rsquo;s gone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quals gave me permission to drop &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. I turned off my email / text / Slack / WhatsApp / calendar reminders / social media. I was in an extremely privileged position to be able to do that for my personal life. But at the time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t recognize how unique this situation would be for my work life. When is it not only acceptable, but highly encouraged, to be &lt;em&gt;that unreachable&lt;/em&gt;? The permission to fully explore a set of ideas was a gift, and not the capital e Examination it was made out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning on my notifications and resuming my other responsibilities shattered my attention. I wanted to keep thinking about those ideas, but I no longer had the socially respected reason to be MIA. I have since abandoned a number of platforms and do everything I can to leave my notifications &amp;ldquo;off&amp;rdquo;, but it is still not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;envisioning-a-different-way-of-doing-quals&#34;&gt;Envisioning a different way of doing quals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The qualifying exam needs some reframing, structurally and colloquially. The exam process should not exist as an Academic Tradition, but something that is student-oriented with specific objectives. If departments &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a so-called weed-out exam, they should reconsider their admissions standards. If departments want to give students an opportunity to demonstrate their subject matter expertise and explore new ideas, they should frame it as such. Here&amp;rsquo;s my vision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advancing to candidacy.  Students will set aside a period of one month to allow for synthetic writing and conversations that will inform the remainder of their dissertation. The writing weeks are a time for uninterrupted deep work and the creation of new theories. Following the written period, students will have 4 hours of undivided attention from their committee &amp;ndash; an opportunity to discuss the ideas in their prospectus and their newly written work with fellow experts. During this month, students will receive full structural support from the department to facilitate uninterrupted deep work, which could include  teaching relief, full time child care, and/or meal vouchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hazing, &lt;a href=&#34;https://hazingprevention.org/home/hazing/facts-what-hazing-looks-like/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;by definition&lt;/a&gt;, includes: (a) &amp;lsquo;a power differential between those in a group and those who want to join a group, or between senior and junior members of a group&amp;rsquo; and (b) &amp;lsquo;an intentional initiation rite, practice or tradition involved&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overall reframing of the qualifying exam ought to (1) acknowledge and minimize the power differential between students and committee members by validating students as subject-matter experts and (2) include carefully crafting the specific objectives of the qualifying exam and turn those objectives into articulated policies within a student handbook. These objectives should be revisited and revised frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should be clear: I did not feel that my qualifying exam came close to hazing. I learned a lot and I am grateful for the experience. But, my experience is not universal. And there is ample room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-tools-and-resources-that-saved-me-during-quals-and-might-help-you-too-&#34;&gt;Some tools and resources that saved me during quals and might help you too :)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com/learn/latex/bibliography_management_with_natbib&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;LaTex + natbib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
s/o to my lab-mate Kristy Ferraro for introducing me to LaTex&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mendeley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evernote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advice from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.azandisresearch.com/2018/05/25/quals/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;older grad students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic pivot projects and learning when to say &#39;no&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/saying-no/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/saying-no/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t say I would recommend doing a PhD during a pandemic. At least, not one that involves travel and working alongside other people. But, a year in, I am doing some reflection on all the ways my research plans and processes have changed, for better and for worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been the Year of Side Projects (aka my pandemic-pivot-projects). Uncertain field seasons, a loudly ticking funding clock, and general loneliness drove my maximizer-tendencies to new heights. I started saying &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo; to &lt;strong&gt;everything&lt;/strong&gt; that came my way, research and otherwise. I told myself I was being strategic; that it was a long term necessity to be &lt;del&gt;flexible and adaptable&lt;/del&gt;. At the start, it felt like floundering. Within a few months, it felt like drowning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
Flexible or floundering?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/12dpLtkNiqc5zO&#34; width=&#34;340&#34; height=&#34;380&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://giphy.com/gifs/animated-dancing-inflatable-12dpLtkNiqc5zO&#34;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the temptation of the side project is nothing new. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to turn down an interesting opportunity, let alone one that involves cool people. But it&amp;rsquo;s doubly hard to turn down an interesting project with cool people, when you have no idea if you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to carry out your planned dissertation. In practice, this meant it was very easy for me to break my own boundaries. My primary challenge was identifying &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to say &amp;rsquo;no&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/gbosslet/status/1120754739346583553&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@gbosslet&amp;rsquo;s decision algorithm&lt;/a&gt; changed my process. It works for research, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found it applies to non-research opportunities as well. For me, it removes all the emotion and second guessing, and helps me enforce the boundaries that make me a more productive scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for my pandemic-pivot-projects. They forced me to pause and think more carefully about my dissertation. They also opened new doors to topics and people that I would&amp;rsquo;ve otherwise left closed. But, they showed me the consequences of saying &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo; too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, saying &amp;rsquo;no&amp;rsquo; is good.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
